Linda Schein Greenebaum Papers, 1930-2009
Sophia Smith Collection
Linda Schein Greenebaum Papers
1930-2009
Greenebaum, Linda Schein
MS 655
4 boxes (1.75 linear ft.)
Sophia Smith Collection Smith College Northampton, MA
Author, Musician, Teacher. The Linda Schein Greenebaum Papers cover the years from her childhood until the present and provide an intimate perspective on the self-described "over-educated and under-distinguished" musician, teacher, writer, and mother. Materials include biographical material, correspondence, writings, diaries, and family history.
Linda Schein Greenebaum was born in Chicago in 1935 to Elizabeth (Cain) and Ernest Schein. Initially raised in Evanston, Illinois, her family moved to Washington D.C. in the mid-1940s. Though her father was of Jewish decent, and her mother's family Episcopalian, the family adopted Christian Science. The failure to seek medical intervention was a factor in the death of a younger sister, Paula, in 1947, of nephritis. The Scheins were a musical family, and Linda played violin, taking advance training in classical music and performing in orchestras and concerts. She graduated as valedictorian from Woodrow Wilson High School in 1952 and attended Radcliffe College, where she majored in European history. She was awarded the A.B. in 1956. She later earned a Master of Arts in Music Education from Smith College in 1978. After her undergraduate work, she travelled to Germany as a Fulbright Scholar. In 1960 she married Michael Greenebaum and settled in the Chicago suburbs. There, and in Cambridge and Amherst, Massachusetts, she raised the couple's four daughters--Sarah, Katherine, Deborah, and Susan. In these years she also gave music lessons and performed with local groups, sometimes with her children. As her children grew older, she took more steady work as a music instructor. Experiencing marital and emotional difficulties, Greenebaum began a journey through therapy, spirituality, and self-help in the 1970s that would continue over the subsequent decades. Her marriage ended in divorce in 1985. Exploring the Jewish and musical heritage of her paternal family, Greenebaum published a family history, Elizer's Troupe: Scheins in America, in 1999. She then converted to Judaism but later drifted from it. A 2008 memoir, Eta Bita Pi, took a frank look at her tumultuous past. She currently lives in Amherst, Massachusetts.
The Linda Schein Greenebaum Papers consist of 1.5 linear feet of material arranged in three series: I. Biographical Material, II. Correspondence, and III. Writings. Covering the years from her childhood until the 2000s, the collection provides an intimate perspective on the self-described "over-educated and under-distinguished" musician, teacher, writer, and mother. Biographical material includes family and personal photographs, clippings, early writings, and music programs. Correspondence mainly documents her childhood years and European travels in the mid-1950s. Schein family history can be found in the biographical material and correspondence as well as her 1999 book, Elizer's Troupe. Greenebaum's diaries provide a rich record of self-reflection over the course of her life, encompassing the subjects of love, loss, profession, religion, and parenting, among others. She recounts such deeply personal events as extramarital affairs and depression. One set of diaries is related to therapy sessions; the other, more day-to-day reflections. Like the diaries, the memoir, Eta Bita Pi, is a candid exploration of her personal and professional development. Additions to the collection are expected.
This collection is organized into four series:
SERIES I. BIOGRAPHICAL MATERIALS
SERIES II. CORRESPONDENCE
SERIES III. WRITINGS
OVERSIZE MATERIALS
The Papers are open to research according to the regulations of the Sophia Smith Collection without any additional restrictions.
Periodic additions to this collection are expected and may not be reflected in this record.
Linda Schein Greenebaum donated her papers to the Sophia Smith Collection in 2009.
Greenebaum, Linda Schein, 1935-; Amherst (Mass.) -- History -- Sources; Musicians -- United States -- Biography -- Sources; Women and psychoanalysis -- History -- Sources; Women authors, American -- Biography -- Sources; Women musicians -- United States -- Biography -- Sources
- SERIES I. BIOGRAPHICAL MATERIALS
  - General, 1954, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Photographs, 1930-90, undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Clippings, 1951-99 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Family histories, 1980-2002, undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Autobiography of Captain W.S. Cain, 1983 [1908] (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Music programs and miscellany, 1950-52, undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Education
    - Report cards, correspondence, and writings, 1940-52 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - High school senior thesis, 1952 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - College thesis, 1956 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Transcripts, resumes, and recommendations, 1978-90 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- SERIES II. CORRESPONDENCE
  - Letters from father and childhood correspondence, 1945-57 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Europe, 1956-57 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Incoming, general, 1953-69, undated (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Christian Science, 1987, undated (Box 1, Folder 14)
- SERIES III. WRITINGS
  - Diaries
    - Senior year of high school, 1952-53 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - First year at Radcliffe, 1953; Europe, 1956-57; Trip to Germany, 1982; and Trip to Austria, 1983 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Pre-divorce, 1984, undated (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - New Age, 1986; Trip to Colorado, 1991; Winter, 1991-92; and Cruise, 2002 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Recent notes and journals, 2009 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Poetry, 1969-2001, undated (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Publications
    - Elizer's Troupe: Scheins in America
      - Published volume, 1999 (Box 2, Folder 6)
      - Publicity and drafts, 1997-99 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Eta Bita Pi: My Inner Sorority
      - Published volume, 2008 (Box 2, Folder 8)
      - Notes and preparation, undated (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Therapy journals
    - Dream journals, 1980-1986 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - General notes, 1980s (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Journals, 1985-92 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Dream therapy, 1990s (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Journals, 1992-2004 (Box 3, Folder 5)
- OVERSIZE MATERIALS
  - Newspapers 1951, 1956 (Box 4)